

I am currently a 5th year Ph.D. candidate in the Computer Science Department at Northwestern University, advised by Prof. Yan Chen. I have a broad interest in various aspects of cloud networks and network protocols. My current research focuses on network optimization of microservices/serverless based cloud. I am also working for introducing formal methods into network protocol verification.

Education

Ph.D. Student in Computer Science Northwestern University

2017 - (2022)

Evanston, IL

- Advisor: Prof. Yan Chen
- Area: Networked System, Cloud Networking, Network Protocols
- Thesis Topic: Configuration Security and Performance Optimization for Network Protocols
- GPA: 3.97/4.00

• Master's in Computer Science

2014 - 2017

Xi'an Jiaotong University

Shaanxi, China

- Advisor: Prof. Chengchen Hu
- Area: Software Defined Networking (SDN)
- Rank: 1st/89 GPA: 3.81/4.00 Average: 91.7

• B.E. in Software Engineering Xi'an Jiaotong University

2010 - 2014

Shaanxi, China

- Rank: 1st/78 GPA: 3.94/4.00 Average: 92.4 (in Junior and Senior years)

Work Experiences

• SRI International Menlo Park, CA

Senior Research Intern, at Computer Science Laboratory

Jun. 2020 - Sep. 2020

- Advisor: Dr. Vinod Yegneswaran and Dr. Phillip Porras
- Real-time anomaly detection with P4 switches and reinforcement learning for NextG networks

• SRI International Menlo Park, CA

Research Intern, at Computer Science Laboratory

Jun. 2020 - Sep. 2020

- Advisor: Dr. <u>Vinod Yegneswaran</u>
- Designed and implemented an enterprise-wide radio situational awareness system
- Passively collected radio traffics, including Wi-Fi and Bluetooth, analyzed by AutoML and nPrint

Research: Cloud Networks & SDN

- Network Optimizing for Microservices/Serverless Cloud (work in progress) 2020 Present
 - Microservices/serverless architectures bring flexibility but introduce network communication delay
 - Integrated QUIC into OpenFaaS/K8s, improved serverless network performance by 28%
 - Designed systematic benchmarks for the microservices network performance measurement
- Generic Security Policy Enforcement System for SDN-based Cloud

2017 - 2018

- Designed a **policy language** for resource protection and management of SDN-based Cloud
- Implemented in the OpenDaylight controller, and deployed on OpenStack

Publication: [IWQoS'18] Lightweight Resource Protection and Management System for SDN-based Cloud

• Routing Policy for Solving Reactive Model Overhead of SDN

2016 - 2017

- SDN control channel bandwidth is the major bottleneck of applying reactive forwarding
- Proposed a routing policy to reduce the SDN control channel bandwidth consumption up to 80%
- Implemented in the Floodlight controller under the OpenFlow/P4 switch and Open vSwitch

Publication: [ICNP'17] SoftRing: Taming the Reactive Model for Software Defined Networks

Research: Formal Methods for Network Protocols

• Formal Verification and Vulnerability Detection of LTE/5G Protocols

2019 - 2020

- Used **TLA+** to formally specify the emergency call systems in **4G/5G** cellular network protocols
- Built a **complete cellular network testbed** (USRP, OpenAirInterface) for real-world verification
- Discovered serious availability and security issues in real-world, acknowledged by major carriers

Publication: [MobiSys'21] Discovering Emergency Call Pitfalls for Cellular Networks with Formal Methods

• Formal Secure Configuration Search for Network Protocols

2020 - 2021

- Traditionally, researchers use secure properties to verify a protocol is safe or find counterexamples
- We convert this decision problem into a search problem. Given the model and the properties, we aim to search the boundaries of the configuration space where the system is always secure and reliable
- We employ inductive generalization and improved IC3 algorithm to determine the space

Publication: [Sigcomm'20 Poster] Network Protocol Safe Configuration Search in One Shot

Publication List

QFaaS: Accelerating and Securing Serverless Cloud Networks with QUIC

Kaiyu Hou, Sen Lin, Yan Chen, Vinod Yegneswaran Under Review, USENIX NSDI, 2022 (NSDI'22)

• Property Guided Secure Configuration Space Search

You Li*, **Kaiyu Hou***, Yan Chen, Hai Zhou (*equal contribution)
Under Review, IEEE International Conference on Computer Communications, 2022 (INFOCOM'22)

• Discovering Emergency Call Pitfalls for Cellular Networks with Formal Methods

Kaiyu Hou*, You Li*, Yinbo Yu, Yan Chen, Hai Zhou (*equal contribution)

ACM 19th International Conference on Mobile Systems, Applications, and Services, 2021 (MobiSys'21)

• Network Protocol Safe Configuration Search in One Shot

You Li*, **Kaiyu Hou***, Hai Zhou, Yan Chen (*equal contribution)

ACM Special Interest Group on Data Communication, Poster, 2020 (SIGCOMM'20)

- State of the Art and Research Challenges in the Security Technologies of Network Function Virtualization Xiaochun Wu, Kaiyu Hou, Xue Leng, Xing Li, Yinbo Yu, Bo Wu, Yan Chen IEEE Internet Computing, 2020
- *CellScope: Automatically Specifying and Verifying Cellular Network Protocols* Yinbo Yu, You Li, **Kaiyu Hou**, Yan Chen, Hai Zhou, Jianfeng Yang ACM Special Interest Group on Data Communication, Poster, 2019 (SIGCOMM'19)
- A Lightweight Policy Enforcement System for Resource Protection and Management in the SDN-based Cloud Xue Leng, Kaiyu Hou, Yan Chen, Kai Bu, Libin Song, You Li Computer Networks, Elsevier, 2019
- *COIN: A fast packet inspection method over compressed traffic* Xiuwen Sun, Hao Li, Dan Zhao, Xingxing Lu, **Kaiyu Hou**, Chengchen Hu Journal of Network and Computer Applications, Elsevier, 2019
- SDNKeeper: Lightweight Resource Protection and Management System for SDN-based Cloud Xue Leng, Kaiyu Hou, Yan Chen, Kai Bu, Libin Song IEEE/ACM 26th International Symposium on Quality of Service, 2018 (IWQoS'18)
- SoftRing: Taming the Reactive Model for Software Defined Networks
 Chengchen Hu, Kaiyu Hou (1st student author), Hao Li, Ruilong Wang, Peng Zheng, Peng Zhang,
 Huanzhao Wang
 IEEE 25th International Conference on Network Protocols, 2017 (ICNP'17)
- Towards A Fast Packet Inspection over Compressed HTTP Traffic
 Xiuwen Sun, Kaiyu Hou, Hao Li, Chengchen Hu
 IEEE/ACM 25th International Symposium on Quality of Service, 2017 (IWQoS'16)

Teaching Experiences

Teaching Assistant, Northwestern University

•	CS 214: Data Structure and Data Management Teaching Assistant, Northwestern University	Spring, 2021
•	CS 214: Data Structure and Data Management Teaching Assistant, Northwestern University	Winter, 2021
•	CS 214: Data Structure and Data Management Teaching Assistant, Northwestern University	Fall, 2020
•	CS 212, Mathematical Foundations of Computer Science	Spring, 2020

 CS 340, Introduction to Networking (Best Teaching Assistant Award) Teaching Assistant, Northwestern University 	Winter, 2020
• CS 214, Data Structure and Data Management Teaching Assistant, Northwestern University	Fall, 2019
• EECS 343, Operating Systems Teaching Assistant, Northwestern University	Spring, 2019
• EECS 340, Introduction to Networking Assistant Lecturer, Northwestern University	Winter, 2019
• EECS 340, Introduction to Networking Teaching Assistant, Northwestern University	Fall, 2018
• IT 458, Information Security and Assurance Teaching Assistant, Northwestern University	Winter, 2018
 Computer Programming (C++) for CS Honored Class Teaching Assistant, Xi'an Jiaotong University 	Fall, 2016
<u>Professional Services</u>	
• Sub-reviewer of ACM ASIA-CCS (2021)	
• Sub-reviewer of ACM CCS (2018, 2019)	
• Sub-reviewer of IEEE ICDCS (2018)	
 Reviewer of IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking (ToN) 	
Awards	
Bronze Medal, ACM-ICPC Asia Regional Contest	2012, 2013, 2014
• Silver Medal, ACM-ICPC China Province Contest, Chengdu	2012, 2013
• Meritorious Winner, Mathematical Contest in Modeling (MCM)	2013
Honor	
• Terminal Year Cabell Fellowship Northwestern University	2021
• Best Teaching Assistant Award (<i>Peter and Adrienne Barris</i> Outstanding TA) <i>Northwestern University</i>	2020
• Outstanding Graduate (Cadre) Award Xi'an Jiaotong University	2017
• Excellent Postgraduate Student Leader Award (each year) Xi'an Jiaotong University	2015, 2016

Outstanding Graduate Award Xi'an Jiaotong University	2014
• Excellent Student Model Nomination (16/13000) Xi'an Jiaotong University	2013
• Google Excellence Scholarship Awarded to 3 students from each of 20 top Chinese universities	2013
• Excellent Student Award (each year) Xi'an Jiaotong University	2011, 2012, 2013
Social Activities	
• Student President of the Computer Science Dept., (Class 2017) <i>Xi'an Jiaotong University</i>	2014 - 2017
• Student Councilor , the Student Congress of ChungYing College <i>Xi'an Jiaotong University</i>	2013 - 2014
• Chair, the ACM-ICPC Club Xi'an Jiaotong University	2012 - 2013
• Science and Education Minister of the Student Union <i>Xi'an Jiaotong University</i>	2011 - 2012
• Co-Founder & the 2 nd Store Manager of Bingo Cafe ChungYing College, Xi'an Jiaotong University	2010 - 2013
Skills	

<u>Skills</u>

- TCP/IP Protocols, 3GPP Cellular Network Protocols (NAS layer), 802.11 Protocols, QUIC Protocol
- Serverless Platforms, Microservices Networks, Cloud Networks, SDN, P4
- Formal Methods for Network Protocols, TLA+, IC3, NuSMV
- Python, Go-lang